I am driven by my longing,
Mieleni minun tekevi,
And my understanding urges
aivoni ajattelevi
That I should commence my singing;
lähteäni laulamahan,
And begin my recitation.
saa'ani sanelemahan,
I will sing the people's legends,
sukuvirttä suoltamahan,
And the ballads of the nation.
lajivirttä laulamahan.
To my mouth the words are flowing,
Sanat suussani sulavat,
And the words are gently falling,
puhe'et putoelevat,
Quickly as my tongue can shape them,
kielelleni kerkiävät,
And between my teeth emerging.
hampahilleni hajoovat.
Dearest friend, and much-loved brother,
Veli kulta, veikkoseni,
Best beloved of all companions,
kaunis kasvinkumppalini!
Come and let us sing together,
Lähe nyt kanssa laulamahan,
Let us now begin our converse,
saa kera sanelemahan
Since at length we meet together,
yhtehen yhyttyämme,
From two widely sundered regions.
kahta'alta käytyämme!
Rarely can we meet together,
Harvoin yhtehen yhymme,
Rarely one can meet the other,
saamme toinen toisihimme
In these dismal Northern regions,
näillä raukoilla rajoilla,
In the dreary land of Pohja.
poloisilla Pohjan mailla.
Let us clasp our hands together,
Lyökämme käsi kätehen,
Let us interlock our fingers;
sormet sormien lomahan,
Let us sing a cheerful measure,
lauloaksemme hyviä,
Let us use our best endeavours,
parahia pannaksemme,
While our dear ones hearken to us,
kuulla noien kultaisien,
And our loved ones are instructed,
tietä mielitehtoisien,
While the young are standing round us,
nuorisossa nousevassa,
Of the rising generation,
kansassa kasuavassa:
Let them learn the words of magic.
noita saamia sanoja,
And recall our songs and legends,
virsiä virittämiä
Of the belt of Väinämöinen,
vyöltä vanhan Väinämöisen,
Of the forge of Ilmarinen,
alta ahjon Ilmarisen,
And of Kaukomieli's sword-point,
päästä kalvan Kaukomielen,
And of Joukahainen's crossbow:
Joukahaisen jousen tiestä,
Of the utmost bounds of Pohja,
Pohjan peltojen periltä,
And of Kalevala's wide heathlands.
Kalevalan kankahilta.
These my father sang aforetime,
Niit' ennen isoni lauloi
As he carved his hatchet's handle,
kirvesvartta vuollessansa;
And my mother taught me likewise,
niitä äitini opetti
As she turned around her spindle,
väätessänsä värttinätä,
When upon the floor, an infant,
minun lasna lattialla
At her knees she saw me tumbling,
eessä polven pyöriessä,
As a helpless child, milk-bearded,
maitopartana pahaisna,
As a babe with mouth all milky.
piimäsuuna pikkaraisna.
Tales about the Sampo failed not,
Sampo ei puuttunut sanoja
Nor the magic spells of Louhi.
eikä Louhi luottehia:
Old at length became the Sampo;
vanheni sanoihin sampo,
Louhi vanished with her magic;
katoi Louhi luottehisin,
Vipunen while singing perished;
virsihin Vipunen kuoli,
Lemminkainen in his follies.
Lemminkäinen leikkilöihin.
There are many other legends;
Viel' on muitaki sanoja,
Songs I learned of magic import;
ongelmoita oppimia:
Some beside the pathway gathered;
tieohesta tempomia,
Others broken from the heather;
kanervoista katkomia,
Others wrested from the bushes;
risukoista riipomia,
Others taken from the saplings,
vesoista vetelemiä,
Gathered from the springing verdure,
päästä heinän hieromia,
Or collected from the by-ways,
raitiolta ratkomia,
As I passed along as herd-boy,
paimenessa käyessäni,
As a child in cattle pastures,
lasna karjanlaitumilla,
On the hillocks, rich in honey,
metisillä mättähillä,
On the hills, for ever golden,
kultaisilla kunnahilla,
After Muurikki, the black one,
mustan Muurikin jälessä,
By the side of dappled Kimmo.
Kimmon kirjavan keralla.
Then the Frost his songs recited,
Vilu mulle virttä virkkoi,
And the rain its legends taught me;
sae saatteli runoja.
Other songs the winds have wafted,
Virttä toista tuulet toivat,
Or the ocean waves have drifted;
meren aaltoset ajoivat.
And their songs the birds have added,
Linnut liitteli sanoja,
And the magic spells the tree-tops.
puien latvat lausehia.
In a ball I bound them tightly;
Ne minä kerälle käärin,
And arranged them in a bundle;
sovittelin sommelolle.
On my little sledge I laid it,
Kerän pistin kelkkahani,
On my sleigh I laid the bundle;
sommelon rekoseheni;
Home upon the sledge I brought it,
ve'in kelkalla kotihin,
Then into the barn conveyed it;
rekosella riihen luoksi;
In the storehouse loft I placed it,
panin aitan parven päähän
In a little box of copper.
vaskisehen vakkasehen.
In the cold my song was resting,
Viikon on virteni vilussa,
Long remained in darkness hidden.
kauan kaihossa sijaisnut.
I must draw the songs from Coldness,
Veänkö vilusta virret,
From the Frost must I withdraw them,
lapan laulut pakkasesta,
Bring my box into the chamber,
tuon tupahan vakkaseni,
On the bench-end lay the casket,
rasian rahin nenähän,
Underneath this noble gable,
alle kuulun kurkihirren,
Underneath this roof of beauty.
alle kaunihin katoksen,
Shall I ope my box of legends,
aukaisen sanaisen arkun,
And my chest where lays are treasured?
virsilippahan viritän,
Is the ball to be unravelled,
kerittelen pään kerältä,
And the bundle's knot unfastened?
suorin solmun sommelolta?
Then I'll sing so grand a ballad,
Niin laulan hyvänki virren,
That it wondrously shall echo,
kaunihinki kalkuttelen
While the ryebread I am eating,
ruoalta rukihiselta,
And the beer of barley drinking.
oluelta ohraiselta.
But though ale should not be brought me,
Kun ei tuotane olutta,
And though beer should not be offered,
tarittane taarivettä,
I will sing, though dry my throttle,
laulan suulta laihemmalta,
Or will sing, with water only,
vetoselta vierettelen
To enhance our evening's pleasure,
tämän iltamme iloksi,
Celebrate the daylight's beauty,
päivän kuulun kunniaksi,
Or the beauty of the daybreak,
vaiko huomenen huviksi,
When another day is dawning.
uuen aamun alkeheksi.
I have often heard related,
Noin kuulin saneltavaksi,
And have heard the song recited,
tiesin virttä tehtäväksi:
How the nights closed ever lonely,
yksin meillä yöt tulevat,
And the days were shining lonely.
yksin päivät valkeavat;
Only born was Väinämöinen,
yksin syntyi Väinämöinen,
And revealed the bard immortal,
ilmestyi ikirunoja
Sprung from the divine Creatrix,
kapehesta kantajasta,
Born of Ilmatar, his mother.
Ilmattaresta emosta.
Air's young daughter was a virgin,
Olipa impi, ilman tyttö,
Fairest daughter of Creation.
kave luonnotar korea.
Long did she abide a virgin,
Piti viikoista pyhyyttä,
All the long days of her girlhood,
iän kaiken impeyttä
In the Air's own spacious mansions,
ilman pitkillä pihoilla,
In those far extending regions.
tasaisilla tanterilla.
Wearily the time passed ever.
Ikävystyi aikojansa,
And her life became a burden,
ouostui elämätänsä,
Dwelling evermore so lonely,
aina yksin ollessansa,
Always living as a maiden,
impenä eläessänsä
In the Air's own spacious mansions,
ilman pitkillä pihoilla,
In those far-extending deserts.
avaroilla autioilla.
After this the maid descending,
Jop' on astuiksen alemma,
Sank upon the tossing billows,
laskeusi lainehille,
On the open ocean's surface,
meren selvälle selälle,
On the wide expanse of water.
ulapalle aukealle.
Then a storm arose in fury,
Tuli suuri tuulen puuska,
From the East a mighty tempest,
iästä vihainen ilma;
And the sea was wildly foaming,
meren kuohuille kohotti,
And the waves dashed ever higher.
lainehille laikahutti.
Thus the tempest rocked the virgin,
Tuuli neittä tuuitteli,
And the billows drove the maiden,
aalto impeä ajeli
O'er the ocean's azure surface,
ympäri selän sinisen,
On the crest of foaming billows,
lakkipäien lainehien:
Till the wind that blew around her,
tuuli tuuli kohtuiseksi,
And the sea woke life within her.
meri paksuksi panevi.
Then she bore her heavy burden,
Kantoi kohtua kovoa,
And the pain it brought upon her,
vatsantäyttä vaikeata
Seven long centuries together,
vuotta seitsemän satoa,
Nine times longer than a lifetime.
yheksän yrön ikeä;
Yet no child was fashioned from her,
eikä synny syntyminen,
And no offspring was perfected.
luovu luomatoin sikiö.
Thus she swam, the Water-Mother,
Vieri impi veen emona.
East she swam, and westward swam she,
Uipi iät, uipi lännet,
Swam to north-west and to south-west,
uipi luotehet, etelät,
And around in all directions,
uipi kaikki ilman rannat
In the sharpness of her torment,
tuskissa tulisen synnyn,
In her body's fearful anguish;
vatsanvaivoissa kovissa;
Yet no child was fashioned from her,
eikä synny syntyminen,
And no offspring was perfected.
luovu luomatoin sikiö.
Then she fell to weeping gently,
Itkeä hyryttelevi;
And in words like these expressed her:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"O how wretched is my fortune,
"Voi poloinen, päiviäni,
Wandering thus, a child unhappy!
lapsi kurja, kulkuani!
I have wandered far already,
Jo olen joutunut johonki:
And I dwell beneath the heaven,
iäkseni ilman alle,
By the tempest tossed for ever,
tuulen tuuiteltavaksi,
While the billows drive me onward.
aaltojen ajeltavaksi
O'er this wide expanse of water,
näillä väljillä vesillä,
On the far-extending billows.
lake'illa lainehilla!
"Better were it had I tarried,
"Parempi olisi ollut
Virgin in aerial regions,
ilman impenä eleä,
Then I should not drift for ever,
kuin on nyt tätä nykyä
As the Mother of the Waters.
vierähellä veen emona:
Here my life is cold and dreary,
vilu tääll' on ollakseni,
Every moment now is painful,
vaiva värjätelläkseni,
Ever tossing on the billows,
aalloissa asuakseni,
Ever floating on the water.
veessä vierielläkseni.
"Ukko, thou of Gods the highest,
"Oi Ukko, ylijumala,
Ruler of the whole of heaven,
ilman kaiken kannattaja!
Hasten here, for thou art needed;
Tule tänne tarvittaissa,
Hasten here at my entreaty.
käy tänne kutsuttaessa!
Free the damsel from her burden,
Päästä piika pintehestä,
And release her from her tortures.
vaimo vatsanvääntehestä!
Quickly haste, and yet more quickly,
Käy pian, välehen jou'u,
Where I long for thee so sorely."
välehemmin tarvitahan!"
Short the time that passed thereafter,
Kului aikoa vähäisen,
Scarce a moment had passed over,
pirahteli pikkaraisen.
Ere a beauteous teal came flying
Tuli sotka, suora lintu;
Lightly hovering o'er the water,
lenteä lekuttelevi
Seeking for a spot to rest in,
etsien pesän sijoa,
Searching for a home to dwell in.
asuinmaata arvaellen.
Eastward flew she, westward flew she.
Lenti iät, lenti lännet,
Flew to north-west and to southward,
lenti luotehet, etelät.
But the place she sought she found not,
Ei löyä tiloa tuota,
Not a spot, however barren,
paikkoa pahintakana,
Where her nest she could establish,
kuhun laatisi pesänsä,
Or a resting-place could light on.
ottaisi olosijansa.
Then she hovered, slowly moving,
Liitelevi, laatelevi;
And she pondered and reflected,
arvelee, ajattelevi:
"If my nest in wind I 'stablish
"Teenkö tuulehen tupani,
Or should rest it on the billows,
aalloillen asuinsijani?
Then the winds will overturn it,
Tuuli kaatavi tupasen,
Or the waves will drift it from me."
aalto vie asuinsijani."
Then the Mother of the Waters,
Niin silloin ve'en emonen,
Water-Mother, maid aerial,
veen emonen, ilman impi,
From the waves her knee uplifted,
nosti polvea merestä,
Raised her shoulder from the billows,
lapaluuta lainehesta
That the teal her nest might 'stablish,
sotkalle pesän sijaksi,
And might find a peaceful dwelling.
asuinmaaksi armahaksi.
Then the teal, the bird so beauteous,
Tuo sotka, sorea lintu,
Hovered slow, and gazed around her,
liiteleikse, laateleikse.
And she saw the knee uplifted
Keksi polven veen emosen
From the blue waves of the ocean,
sinerväisellä selällä;
And she thought she saw a hillock,
luuli heinämättähäksi,
Freshly green with springing verdure.
tuoreheksi turpeheksi.
There she flew, and hovered slowly,
Lentelevi, liitelevi,
Gently on the knee alighting,
päähän polven laskeuvi.
And her nest she there established,
Siihen laativi pesänsä,
And she laid her eggs all golden,
muni kultaiset munansa:
Six gold eggs she laid within it,
kuusi kultaista munoa,
And a seventh she laid of iron.
rautamunan seitsemännen.
O'er her eggs the teal sat brooding,
Alkoi hautoa munia,
And the knee grew warm beneath her;
päätä polven lämmitellä.
And she sat one day, a second,
Hautoi päivän, hautoi toisen,
Brooded also on the third day;
hautoi kohta kolmannenki.
Then the Mother of the Waters,
Jopa tuosta veen emonen,
Water-Mother, maid aerial,
veen emonen, ilman impi,
Felt it hot, and felt it hotter,
tuntevi tulistuvaksi,
And she felt her skin was heated,
hipiänsä hiiltyväksi;
Till she thought her knee was burning,
luuli polvensa palavan,
And that all her veins were melting.
kaikki suonensa sulavan.
Then she jerked her knee with quickness,
Vavahutti polveansa,
And her limbs convulsive shaking,
järkytti jäseniänsä:
Rolled the eggs into the water,
munat vierähti vetehen,
Down amid the waves of ocean,
meren aaltohon ajaikse;
And to splinters they were broken,
karskahti munat muruiksi,
And to fragments they were shattered.
katkieli kappaleiksi.
In the ooze they were not wasted,
Ei munat mutahan joua,
Nor the fragments in the water,
siepalehet veen sekahan.
But a wondrous change came o'er them,
Muuttuivat murut hyviksi,
And the fragments all grew lovely.
kappalehet kaunoisiksi:
From the cracked egg's lower fragment,
munasen alainen puoli
Now the solid earth was fashioned,
alaiseksi maaemäksi,
From the cracked egg's upper fragment,
munasen yläinen puoli
Rose the lofty arch of heaven,
yläiseksi taivahaksi;
From the yolk, the upper portion,
yläpuoli ruskeaista
Now became the sun's bright lustre;
päivöseksi paistamahan,
From the white, the upper portion,
yläpuoli valkeaista,
Rose the moon that shines so brightly;
se kuuksi kumottamahan;
Whatso in the egg was mottled,
mi munassa kirjavaista,
Now became the stars in heaven,
ne tähiksi taivahalle,
Whatso in the egg was blackish,
mi munassa mustukaista,
In the air as cloudlets floated.
nepä ilman pilvilöiksi.
Now the time passed quickly over,
Ajat eellehen menevät,
And the years rolled quickly onward,
vuoet tuota tuonnemmaksi
In the new sun's shining lustre,
uuen päivän paistaessa,
In the new moon's softer beaming.
uuen kuun kumottaessa.
Still the Water-Mother floated,
Aina uipi veen emonen,
Water-Mother, maid aerial,
veen emonen, ilman impi,
Ever on the peaceful waters,
noilla vienoilla vesillä,
On the billows' foamy surface,
utuisilla lainehilla,
With the moving waves before her,
eessänsä vesi vetelä,
And the heaven serene behind her.
takanansa taivas selvä.
When the ninth year had passed over,
Jo vuonna yheksäntenä,
And the summer tenth was passing,
kymmenentenä kesänä
From the sea her head she lifted,
nosti päätänsä merestä,
And her forehead she uplifted,
kohottavi kokkoansa.
And she then began Creation,
Alkoi luoa luomiansa,
And she brought the world to order,
saautella saamiansa
On the open ocean's surface,
selvällä meren selällä,
On the far extending waters.
ulapalla aukealla.
Wheresoe'er her hand she pointed,
Kussa kättä käännähytti,
There she formed the jutting headlands;
siihen niemet siivoeli;
Wheresoe'er her feet she rested,
kussa pohjasi jalalla,
There she formed the caves for fishes;
kalahauat kaivaeli;
When she dived beneath the water,
kussa ilman kuplistihe,
There she formed the depths of ocean;
siihen syöverit syventi.
When towards the land she turned her,
Kylin maahan kääntelihe:
There the level shores extended,
siihen sai sileät rannat;
Where her feet to land extended,
jaloin maahan kääntelihe:
Spots were formed for salmon-netting;
siihen loi lohiapajat;
Where her head the land touched lightly,
pä'in päätyi maata vasten:
There the curving bays extended.
siihen laitteli lahelmat.
Further from the land she floated,
Ui siitä ulomma maasta,
And abode in open water,
seisattelihe selälle:
And created rocks in ocean,
luopi luotoja merehen,
And the reefs that eyes behold not,
kasvatti salakaria
Where the ships are often shattered,
laivan laskemasijaksi,
And the sailors' lives are ended.
merimiesten pään menoksi.
Now the isles were formed already,
Jo oli saaret siivottuna,
In the sea the rocks were planted;
luotu luotoset merehen,
Pillars of the sky established,
ilman pielet pistettynä,
Lands and continents created;
maat ja manteret sanottu,
Rocks engraved as though with figures,
kirjattu kivihin kirjat,
And the hills were cleft with fissures.
veetty viivat kallioihin.
Still unborn was Väinämöinen;
Viel' ei synny Väinämöinen,
Still unborn, the bard immortal.
ilmau ikirunoja.
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Rested in his mother's body
kulki äitinsä kohussa
For the space of thirty summers,
kolmekymmentä keseä,
And the sum of thirty winters,
yhen verran talviaki,
Ever on the placid waters,
noilla vienoilla vesillä,
And upon the foaming billows.
utuisilla lainehilla.
So he pondered and reflected
Arvelee, ajattelevi,
How he could continue living
miten olla, kuin eleä
In a resting-place so gloomy,
pimeässä piilossansa,
In a dwelling far too narrow,
asunnossa ahtahassa,
Where he could not see the moonlight,
kuss' ei konsa kuuta nähnyt
Neither could behold the sunlight.
eikä päiveä havainnut.
Then he spake the words which follow,
Sanovi sanalla tuolla,
And expressed his thoughts in this wise:
lausui tuolla lausehella:
"Aid me Moon, and Sun release me,
"Kuu, keritä, päivyt, päästä,
And the Great Bear lend his counsel,
otava, yhä opeta
Through the portal that I know not,
miestä ouoilta ovilta,
Through the unaccustomed passage.
veräjiltä vierahilta,
From the little nest that holds me,
näiltä pieniltä pesiltä,
From a dwelling-place so narrow,
asunnoilta ahtahilta!
To the land conduct the roamer,
Saata maalle matkamiestä,
To the open air conduct me,
ilmoillen inehmon lasta,
To behold the moon in heaven,
kuuta taivon katsomahan,
And the splendour of the sunlight;
päiveä ihoamahan,
See the Great Bear's stars above me,
otavaista oppimahan,
And the shining stars in heaven."
tähtiä tähyämähän!"
When the moon no freedom gave him,
Kun ei kuu kerittänynnä
Neither did the sun release him,
eikä päivyt päästänynnä,
Then he wearied of existence,
ouosteli aikojansa,
And his life became a burden.
tuskastui elämätänsä:
Thereupon he moved the portal,
liikahutti linnan portin
With his finger, fourth in number,
sormella nimettömällä,
Opened quick the bony gateway,
lukon luisen luikahutti
With the toes upon his left foot,
vasemmalla varpahalla;
With his nails beyond the threshold,
tuli kynsin kynnykseltä,
With his knees beyond the gateway.
polvin porstuan ovelta.
Headlong in the water falling,
Siitä suistui suin merehen,
With his hands the waves repelling,
käsin kääntyi lainehesen;
Thus the man remained in ocean,
jääpi mies meren varahan,
And the hero on the billows.
uros aaltojen sekahan.
In the sea five years he sojourned,
Virui siellä viisi vuotta,
Waited five years, waited six years,
sekä viisi jotta kuusi,
Seven years also, even eight years,
vuotta seitsemän, kaheksan.
On the surface of the ocean,
Seisottui selälle viimein,
By a nameless promontory,
niemelle nimettömälle,
Near a barren, treeless country.
manterelle puuttomalle.
On the land his knees he planted,
Polvin maasta ponnistihe,
And upon his arms he rested,
käsivarsin käännältihe.
Rose that he might view the moonbeams,
Nousi kuuta katsomahan,
And enjoy the pleasant sunlight,
päiveä ihoamahan,
See the Great Bear's stars above him,
otavaista oppimahan,
And the shining stars in heaven.
tähtiä tähyämähän.
Thus was ancient Väinämöinen,
Se oli synty Väinämöisen,
He, the ever famous minstrel,
rotu rohkean runojan
Born of the divine Creatrix,
kapehesta kantajasta,
Born of Ilmatar, his mother.
Ilmattaresta emosta.